<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Resolutions | Aashay.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/categories/resolutions/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aashay.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-14T01:00:30-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://aashay.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aashay Desai]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2013 and 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2014/01/13/new-years-resolutions-2013-and-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-13T23:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2014/01/13/new-years-resolutions-2013-and-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been blogging on and off on this site for many years, and the site itself has gone through several iterations.  Even after a long hiatus, however, I'd still remember to come back and post my <a href="http://aashay.com/blog/2010/09/29/new-year-s-resolutions-2011/">New Year's</a> <a href="http://aashay.com/blog/2012/01/01/new-year-s-resolutions-2012/">Resolutions</a>.</p>

<p>Astute readers of this site (all two of you) will have noticed that I never posted anything in 2013.  The reason behind this was simple:  I wanted 2013 to be a different year.</p>

<p>2013 was all about serendipity.  I decide to simply "go with the flow" and see where life took me.  It certainly wasn't all roses, but fortunately, even the negative things that happened gave me some perspective on how to grow as a person.</p>

<p>2014 is going to be the exact opposite.  I have one resolution, and while it sounds simple, it's going to be an incredible challenge:  Be In Control.</p>

<p>This year, I intend to be in full control of my life situation at all times.  This will mean making all kinds of tough decisions, including cutting out people, places, and things that aren't helping me grow.  More importantly, being in control means leaving nothing to chance and not letting others determine my future for me.</p>

<p>I know it all sounds a little self-helpy, but given the various events of 2013, it's clearly the number one thing I need to keep in mind.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2012/01/01/new-year-s-resolutions-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2012/01/01/new-year-s-resolutions-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Once again I'm posting my New Year's Resolutions somewhere public (my blog) so that I'm more likely to follow them. My resolutions this year are the same as last year's with one noteable exception.</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Last year I made some <a href="http://aashay.com/Kaizen/Resolutions/2010/09/29/new-year-s-resolutions-2011.html">pretty basic resolutions</a>. I made great progress on some and not-so-great progress on others, but this year there's very little different I want to do, with one noteable exception.</p>

<p>To recap:</p>

<ul>
<li>Get Healthy (work out)</li>
<li>Keep better tabs on my finances</li>
<li>Write (I fail at this one every year)</li>
<li>Kaizen (general self-improvement)</li>
</ul>


<p>If there's one thing I'd like to add to the list:</p>

<ul>
<li>Balance.</li>
</ul>


<p>I've fallen into the habit of spending a lot of time working on one subset of skills and talents that I tend to let others fall behind.  Specifically, I'd like to tap back into my creative side (vis a vis music) while I continue to improve my hacking chops.  Ideally, this means taking both sides to an extreme.</p>

<p>I'd like to write at least <em>one</em> song this year and start at least <em>one</em> open-source project (hopefully something that develops as a result of my work with <a href="http://anonymou.se">AnonyMou.se</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2010/09/29/new-year-s-resolutions-2011/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2010/09/29/new-year-s-resolutions-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I’ve made it a tradition to post my <a href="http://www.aashay.com/2010/01/04/new-years-resolutions-2010/">New Year's Resolutions here</a> on my blog.  The idea is that if they’re posted somewhere public, I’ll be more likely to follow them.  This year, I’m going to do a recap of last year’s resolutions and see which ones I’ve kept and which ones I’ve broken.</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I didn’t do so bad this year!  Let’s take a look at my New Year’s resolutions from 2010 and see how I managed to do:</p>

<ul style="list-style-type: disc;">
    <li>Save money.  Lots of it. - <em>I think I did pretty well here.</em></li>
    <li>"Level up" in mastery of my instruments (this means noticeable improvements) <em>- This one is hard to judge by myself, but my bandmates seem pretty happy with my skill.</em></li>
    <li>Overcome this epic writer's block and write something - <em>Epic fail.</em></li>
    <li>Continue to exercise and try and increase my <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="http://www.matchmakertennis.com/public/ntrp.html">NTRP rating</a></span> by summer - <em>Although I did manage to increase my NTRP rating, I’ve fallen off the tennis boat in favor for more traditional forms of exercise.</em></li>
    <li>Focus on projects that matter, including one major to-be-determined <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Hairy_Audacious_Goal">Big Hairy Audacious Goal</a></span> - <em>I did pretty well last year but this coming year is the real determining year.</em></li>
    <li>Focus on the people that matter - <em>A perpetual goal, I’d say I did just fine</em></li>
    <li>Stimulate my career path - <em>Yep.</em></li>
</ul>


<p>So of all the resolutions, I managed to only break the writing one.  Oddly enough I did the same thing in 2009.</p>

<p>Now let’s take a look at my resolutions for 2011.</p>

<ul style="list-style-type: disc;">
    <li><strong>Get healthy. </strong> I’ve recently discovered that I might not be in the most perfect state of health, so this year my focus is to drastically change my diet and exercise habits.  Fortunately I got a head start a few weeks ago on this one so I don’t think this’ll be very hard to maintain.</li>
    <li><strong>Continue saving money. </strong> I didn’t do so bad last year but this year I’m going to be taking even more aggressive steps to save, including making some smart investments.</li>
    <li><strong>Write damnit! </strong> I know I tell everyone I’m going to do this every year, but this year I mean it.  I’ve recently started journaling and hopefully I’ll post some of my better essays on this blog.  I’m also considering starting up a secondary “nerd” blog to write about my misadventures in hacking on my personal projects, but I’m still working on the logistics (i.e. whether or not they’ll be posted here).</li>
    <li><strong>Kaizen</strong> aka Continual self-improvement.  I need to improve any existing talents, including (but not limited to) music and hacking.  The latter especially will help with career moves.</li>
    <li><strong>Learn something new. </strong>I’d like to add another skill to my plate this year, and I’m thinking it might have to do with cooking.  Fortunately I’ve got a wonderful partner-in-crime for this particular endeavor, and learning to cook will help me out with resolution 1 as well.</li>
</ul>


<p>So, there you have it.  Now let’s hear your resolutions!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2010]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2010/01/04/new-year-s-resolutions-2010/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2010/01/04/new-year-s-resolutions-2010</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Last year I posted my </em><a href="http://www.aashay.com/2009/01/01/new-years-resolutions" target="_blank">New Year's Resolutions here</a>, and I'm proud to say that I managed to follow most of them (although not all of them).  I'm doing the same this year.</em></p>

<!-- more -->




<div id="_mcePaste">Of my New Year's Resolutions from 2009, I managed to actually accomplish all but 2 (I never did get to contribute to an open-source project, and I definitely haven't written anything new).   I figure I might as well tell you the plan for this year:</div>


<div id="_mcePaste">
<ul>
    <li>Save money.  Lots of it.</li>
    <li>"Level up" in mastery of my instruments (this means noticeable improvements)</li>
    <li>Overcome this epic writer's block and write something</li>
    <li>Continue to exercise and try and increase my <a href="http://www.matchmakertennis.com/public/ntrp.html" target="_blank">NTRP rating</a> by summer</li>
    <li>Focus on projects that matter, including one major to-be-determined <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Hairy_Audacious_Goal" target="_blank">Big Hairy Audacious Goal </a></li>
    <li>Focus on the people that matter</li>
    <li>Stimulate my career path</li>
</ul>
</div>


<p>Let's hear your resolutions for this year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2009]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2009/01/02/new-year-s-resolutions/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2009/01/02/new-year-s-resolutions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Normally I post long-form essays here on my site.  However, I figured if I exposed my New Year's Resolutions somewhere public, I might be more prone to follow them.</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I wrote down my New Year's resolutions in one of my <a href="http://www.evernote.com" target="_blank">Evernote</a> notebooks, but I figure I'd share them with you all.  I'd say they're pretty realistic and hopefully I won't have problems sticking to 'em.  So, without further ado:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Practice guitar/bass for a total of 5 hours a week, minimum</li>
    <li>Compose music again</li>
    <li>Write more (both blog essays and hopefully restart the fiction work too)</li>
    <li>Talk to strangers more (and meet more people in SF)</li>
    <li>Exercise (I'm sure I'll be more motivated when my <a href="http://www.fitbit.com" target="_blank">FitBit</a> arrives)</li>
    <li>Contribute to an open-source project</li>
    <li>Get a raise/promotion at (or before) my 1-year anniversary at my company</li>
</ul>


<p>What were your New Year's resolutions?  Post some in the comments section (or in the Notes comments if you're reading this via Facebook)!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
