<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Kaizen | Aashay.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/categories/kaizen/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aashay.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-03T01:55:18-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://aashay.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aashay Desai]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2012/01/01/new-year-s-resolutions-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2012/01/01/new-year-s-resolutions-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Once again I'm posting my New Year's Resolutions somewhere public (my blog) so that I'm more likely to follow them. My resolutions this year are the same as last year's with one noteable exception.</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Last year I made some <a href="http://aashay.com/Kaizen/Resolutions/2010/09/29/new-year-s-resolutions-2011.html">pretty basic resolutions</a>. I made great progress on some and not-so-great progress on others, but this year there's very little different I want to do, with one noteable exception.</p>

<p>To recap:</p>

<ul>
<li>Get Healthy (work out)</li>
<li>Keep better tabs on my finances</li>
<li>Write (I fail at this one every year)</li>
<li>Kaizen (general self-improvement)</li>
</ul>


<p>If there's one thing I'd like to add to the list:</p>

<ul>
<li>Balance.</li>
</ul>


<p>I've fallen into the habit of spending a lot of time working on one subset of skills and talents that I tend to let others fall behind.  Specifically, I'd like to tap back into my creative side (vis a vis music) while I continue to improve my hacking chops.  Ideally, this means taking both sides to an extreme.</p>

<p>I'd like to write at least <em>one</em> song this year and start at least <em>one</em> open-source project (hopefully something that develops as a result of my work with <a href="http://anonymou.se">AnonyMou.se</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2010/09/29/new-year-s-resolutions-2011/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2010/09/29/new-year-s-resolutions-2011</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I’ve made it a tradition to post my <a href="http://www.aashay.com/2010/01/04/new-years-resolutions-2010/">New Year's Resolutions here</a> on my blog.  The idea is that if they’re posted somewhere public, I’ll be more likely to follow them.  This year, I’m going to do a recap of last year’s resolutions and see which ones I’ve kept and which ones I’ve broken.</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I didn’t do so bad this year!  Let’s take a look at my New Year’s resolutions from 2010 and see how I managed to do:</p>

<ul style="list-style-type: disc;">
    <li>Save money.  Lots of it. - <em>I think I did pretty well here.</em></li>
    <li>"Level up" in mastery of my instruments (this means noticeable improvements) <em>- This one is hard to judge by myself, but my bandmates seem pretty happy with my skill.</em></li>
    <li>Overcome this epic writer's block and write something - <em>Epic fail.</em></li>
    <li>Continue to exercise and try and increase my <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="http://www.matchmakertennis.com/public/ntrp.html">NTRP rating</a></span> by summer - <em>Although I did manage to increase my NTRP rating, I’ve fallen off the tennis boat in favor for more traditional forms of exercise.</em></li>
    <li>Focus on projects that matter, including one major to-be-determined <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Hairy_Audacious_Goal">Big Hairy Audacious Goal</a></span> - <em>I did pretty well last year but this coming year is the real determining year.</em></li>
    <li>Focus on the people that matter - <em>A perpetual goal, I’d say I did just fine</em></li>
    <li>Stimulate my career path - <em>Yep.</em></li>
</ul>


<p>So of all the resolutions, I managed to only break the writing one.  Oddly enough I did the same thing in 2009.</p>

<p>Now let’s take a look at my resolutions for 2011.</p>

<ul style="list-style-type: disc;">
    <li><strong>Get healthy. </strong> I’ve recently discovered that I might not be in the most perfect state of health, so this year my focus is to drastically change my diet and exercise habits.  Fortunately I got a head start a few weeks ago on this one so I don’t think this’ll be very hard to maintain.</li>
    <li><strong>Continue saving money. </strong> I didn’t do so bad last year but this year I’m going to be taking even more aggressive steps to save, including making some smart investments.</li>
    <li><strong>Write damnit! </strong> I know I tell everyone I’m going to do this every year, but this year I mean it.  I’ve recently started journaling and hopefully I’ll post some of my better essays on this blog.  I’m also considering starting up a secondary “nerd” blog to write about my misadventures in hacking on my personal projects, but I’m still working on the logistics (i.e. whether or not they’ll be posted here).</li>
    <li><strong>Kaizen</strong> aka Continual self-improvement.  I need to improve any existing talents, including (but not limited to) music and hacking.  The latter especially will help with career moves.</li>
    <li><strong>Learn something new. </strong>I’d like to add another skill to my plate this year, and I’m thinking it might have to do with cooking.  Fortunately I’ve got a wonderful partner-in-crime for this particular endeavor, and learning to cook will help me out with resolution 1 as well.</li>
</ul>


<p>So, there you have it.  Now let’s hear your resolutions!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2010]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2010/01/04/new-year-s-resolutions-2010/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2010/01/04/new-year-s-resolutions-2010</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Last year I posted my </em><a href="http://www.aashay.com/2009/01/01/new-years-resolutions" target="_blank">New Year's Resolutions here</a>, and I'm proud to say that I managed to follow most of them (although not all of them).  I'm doing the same this year.</em></p>

<!-- more -->




<div id="_mcePaste">Of my New Year's Resolutions from 2009, I managed to actually accomplish all but 2 (I never did get to contribute to an open-source project, and I definitely haven't written anything new).   I figure I might as well tell you the plan for this year:</div>


<div id="_mcePaste">
<ul>
    <li>Save money.  Lots of it.</li>
    <li>"Level up" in mastery of my instruments (this means noticeable improvements)</li>
    <li>Overcome this epic writer's block and write something</li>
    <li>Continue to exercise and try and increase my <a href="http://www.matchmakertennis.com/public/ntrp.html" target="_blank">NTRP rating</a> by summer</li>
    <li>Focus on projects that matter, including one major to-be-determined <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Hairy_Audacious_Goal" target="_blank">Big Hairy Audacious Goal </a></li>
    <li>Focus on the people that matter</li>
    <li>Stimulate my career path</li>
</ul>
</div>


<p>Let's hear your resolutions for this year!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Year's Resolutions 2009]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2009/01/02/new-year-s-resolutions/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2009/01/02/new-year-s-resolutions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Normally I post long-form essays here on my site.  However, I figured if I exposed my New Year's Resolutions somewhere public, I might be more prone to follow them.</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I wrote down my New Year's resolutions in one of my <a href="http://www.evernote.com" target="_blank">Evernote</a> notebooks, but I figure I'd share them with you all.  I'd say they're pretty realistic and hopefully I won't have problems sticking to 'em.  So, without further ado:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Practice guitar/bass for a total of 5 hours a week, minimum</li>
    <li>Compose music again</li>
    <li>Write more (both blog essays and hopefully restart the fiction work too)</li>
    <li>Talk to strangers more (and meet more people in SF)</li>
    <li>Exercise (I'm sure I'll be more motivated when my <a href="http://www.fitbit.com" target="_blank">FitBit</a> arrives)</li>
    <li>Contribute to an open-source project</li>
    <li>Get a raise/promotion at (or before) my 1-year anniversary at my company</li>
</ul>


<p>What were your New Year's resolutions?  Post some in the comments section (or in the Notes comments if you're reading this via Facebook)!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Changes]]></title>
    <link href="http://aashay.com/blog/2008/12/29/changes/"/>
    <updated>2008-12-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aashay.com/blog/2008/12/29/changes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>In this post, I discuss a few major life changes I've recently made, the stimulus for the change, and my plans for the immediate future.</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I haven't worked on any computer projects in a few weeks. I haven't written a new essay in a few months. I haven't written a new original song or worked on my short stories in a few years. One morning I woke up realizing all of these things at once and I decided that something wasn't right.  Was it a lack of creativity?  Motivation perhaps?  Well, it turns out that it was a combination of both. But what could be causing such a drain?</p>

<p>It turns out that it was my job.</p>

<p>A few months ago, I quit my job and moved to the Bay Area for a brand new one.  Some people found this change to be a bit drastic, but as I'll explain later in this essay, it was a decision in progress for several months. I came to realize that my job left me little time or energy to work on my own projects, and that coupled with general career path dissatisfaction made me decide that it was time to move on.  I'd like to provide a basic summary of what I did, and why.</p>

<h2>So what is it that you do here?</h2>


<p>I graduated engineering school with a degree involving a healthy blend of business and nerdery.  Most people know that I'm in the software industry, yet don't realize that I did not graduate with a degree in Computer Science. I made that move specifically so that I got a lot more exposure to the business side of engineering, and it was definitely the right move. So naturally after I graduated I decided to pursue the best of both worlds.</p>

<p>Consulting was a great fit, and so I managed to land myself a pretty hip gig traveling to the west coast working on, you guessed it, business software.  I went to clients, talked about their business needs, put on headphones, and crafted solutions out of thin air.</p>

<p>I got a lot of exposure to the whole "real world" thing, but I also learned a lot about the niche I was in.  I busted ass, and I'd say I was pretty decent at what I did.  I made senior in a year, which was pretty cool, since that doesn't happen too much at my former company.</p>

<p>When I told my manager I was leaving, it was pretty evident that he didn't see it coming.  He explained to me that I was on the "fast track" at my company and in my career, and that I should be absolutely sure of what I'm doing before making such a drastic career change.</p>

<p>So why'd I jump ship?</p>

<h2>Didn't you get the memo?</h2>


<p>I'm going to let you in on a few secrets.  Most common folks don't know anything about ERP, CRM, PLM, B2B, B2C, or any other fancy acronyms you throw at them.  All they know is that they get paid to go to work, and sometimes they spend that money on things.  The business world has a very ornate ecosystem that, for some reason, works like an echo chamber.  Everyone in it can hear each other to some degree, but anyone outside of it is blissfully unaware of how it affects them.</p>

<p>When you go to the store to buy something, you're buying directly from a business.  We call that "Business to Consumer" or B2C for short.  However, that business can't do everything on its own to sell you that product (no, not even Apple.  Looooove yooou!) and so it has to depend on other businesses to help it along the way.  The interaction between businesses (business-to-business, or B2B) is the space I'm in, and it's a different monster from the B2C interactions that we are all used to.</p>

<p>That thing you bought at the store?  Well it wasn't always there.  It got shipped there, and so that involved some sort of shipping logistics.  Someone had to purchase that thing from some vendor, or perhaps put in an order at some overseas manufacturing facility, so now we're talking about procurement or perhaps production.  Clearly there was money involved, so that means financials.  Obviously a bunch of human beings were involved in this and so now we're talking about human resources.  Maybe there were some sales guys involved in cutting a deal to get that product to the stores and in your hands, so that means some sort of customer relationship management.</p>

<p>If all of this sounds complex, it's because it is.  Being the enginerd I am, I'm attracted to complex systems.  The unfortunate part about these <em>complex</em> systems is that they are also usually <em>complicated</em>.  But, that doesn't mean they have to be.</p>

<h2>It's not that I'm lazy.  It's that I don't care.</h2>


<p><span>Business software doesn't evolve as rapidly as consumer software.</span> However, in the past few years, a handful of really bright people decided to take unique approaches to some common complexities.  They decided "Hey, we're going to do this differently" and of course their well-established counterparts scoffed.  They found a way to deliver business software without the typical overhead and up-front costs to the customer, and Software-as-a-Service was born.</p>

<p>My former company is, by design, affiliated with one of those well-established counterparts.  So, when I was sent out to help folks with their businesses, they had to play by our rules, which were the rules passed down by our king company.  We used a specific platform, did things a specific way, and used the same playbooks over and over for completely different businesses.  Also, the tools and technology we used were designed for very specific purposes.</p>

<p>I think most good technologists don't like being tied down like this, especially early on in their careers.  I suppose if I stuck around, I would've become a total guru at doing what I was doing.  But that would've just turned me into a magician with one good magic trick, and that's not the career path I wanted to head down.</p>

<p>I don't want to be such a specialist.  I want to experience a wide variety of technologies, tools, and tricks of the trade.  I want to expand my horizons and work with the absolute best.  That handful of really bright people who take unique approaches have created astounding companies that have developed revolutionary technology- and I want to be a part of that wave.  Knowing about it and not being a part of it caused me to become a bit stagnant.</p>

<p>Of course, there were other reasons besides wanting to hang out with the cool kids that made me make the switch.</p>

<h2>Deeper and deeper.  Way down.</h2>


<p>Few people would argue against the statement that the San Francisco Bay Area (which includes Silicon Valley) is filled with some of the country's brightest minds.  I always try to be around smart people, and while the folks I previously worked with were quite smart (and thanks to the hours I worked, I was definitely around them quite a bit), there was something about the Bay Area vibe that caught my attention.  Moving to the Bay Area was an obvious choice.</p>

<p>I managed to get lucky in that my last project, before I quit, was in the Bay Area, and I stayed at a place in San Francisco while on it.  However, just because I resided in San Francisco didn't mean I "lived" in San Francisco.  My job's long hours and travel schedule were hardly conducive to any sort of social lifestyle out here, and that was a problem.</p>

<p>My former company was also having issues of its own.  Retention was poor, possibly because of "the economy" or the shifts in the company direction.  Nobody really knows even today, but the point is that the situation was looking a bit grim.  While my particular position was secure (at least, I assumed as much), all the nervous energy made it apparent that I needed a backup plan.</p>

<p>I found a position at my new company (I still need to talk to our PR department to see if it's okay for me to disclose the name, will post an update later if possible) that lets me build things that help other people by making their work lives easier, and allows me to work in a stimulating environment with intelligent people.  So the question that remains is, what's next?</p>

<h2>I wouldn't say I've been missing it, Bob</h2>


<p>Some of you may be wondering if I miss the perks that came with my consulting job. Don't I miss the basically-free travel, hotel and airline points, and nomad lifestyle? Meh, not really.  I'm not going to lie and say that the next five years of my life are planned out.  Sure, there's a possibility of me getting back into the consulting gig some day.  There's even the possibility of me not being in the software realm in the future.  It's pretty hard to tell where I'll be, but that's not to say I don't have a vision for the future.</p>

<p>It's no secret that I'm aligning myself to either create or be a part of a start-up some day.  Until that happens, I can only absorb as much knowledge as possible and develop skills along the way to prepare me for those days.  I'm pretty sure that my recent career move is only going to help in that respect.  I almost make it sound like I've got some sort of career commitment phobia, but rest assured, as long as I'm being intellectually stimulated, working on a kickass product, and working with brilliant people, I'll be quite happy.</p>

<p>Now, what these decisions are going to do for my comatose creative life is still a toss-up...but I suppose I've already taken the first step.</p>

<p>Special thanks to <a href="http://www.dashofstash.com" target="_blank">Mike Stashwick</a> for reading drafts of this essay.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
